Examples of encryption persist throughout human
history from early cryptic depictions by
cave dwellers of Magura cave in Bulgaria to the pyramids at Giza.
Even then each group had its own primitive cryptographic approach
so that members of the tribe or group could communicate
with one another while keeping secrets from the rival tribes
regarding hunting grounds or sources of water and food.
It is part of human nature to encrypt information.
You start with clear text, which is the information that you and I could easily read
and then you use an algorithm which is often a
form of software that can be embedded in the system,
but that needs to be activated with an encryption key.
A very simple example is if you are trying to encrypt a PDF document, for example,
perhaps your accountant is sending you some
documents to sign before submitting your taxes.
Encryption would create a cipher text which no one can use.
And you and your accountant would have set up a preset encryption key
so that you could retrieve the information at either end of the communication,
you need to have good key management, which means you safeguard the information
because imagine if you have thousands of keys in a commercial environment,
there is often a third party or external server
where the keys will be separately stored and managed.
So you don't have all your eggs in one basket, so to speak,
it will be protected through a hashing system
and no one else can have access to those keys.
Asymmetric encryption is more secure because the sender
and receiver each uses a unique code,
often a certificate.
So you can confirm that the information has been sent
from the sender to the recipient in a secure manner.